Chris Gorgolewski

Co-director of the Stanford Center for Reproducible Neuroscience Research Associate at Department of Psychology, Stanford University

Address: 450 Serra Mall, Stanford

CA 94305, USA

Email: krzysztof.gorgolewski@gmail.com Passport name: Krzysztof Jacek Gorgolewski

Nationality: Polish

US immigration
H1-B, green card application pending (I-140 approved)

status:

Research Interests

I am interested in we can use modern technology to improve the way we study human behaviour and its neuronal underpinnings. This involves building tools and services (such as Nipype, OpenNeuro, and NeuroVault.org) that allow neuroscientists, psychologist and clinicians to be more efficient and less biased in the way they collect, share and analyze data. I'm also involved efforts to maximise the impact of behavioural and brain research through data sharing. This work goes beyond tools and services, also including policy making and publishing culture research.

Postdoctoral Work Experience

2015 – Center for Reproducible Neuroscience, Stanford University, USA

Co-director http://reproducibility.stanford.edu

2015 - Stanford University, Stanford, USA

Research Associate

Russell Poldrack Lab, Department of Psychology

2014 – 2015 Stanford University, Stanford, USA

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Russell Poldrack Lab, Department of Psychology

2012 – 2014 Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences, Leipzig, Germany

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Neuroanatomy and Connectivity Research Group

Education

2017 Stanford Manager Academy

A development program designed to enhance the effectiveness of staff managers at all levels of

experience and create a community of managers across the university.

2009 – 2012 University of Edinburgh, UK

PhD in Neuroimaging Methods

Thesis topic "Using probabilistic models of white and grey matter activation for presurgical planning of

tumour extraction", supervisors: Mark Bastin, Cyril Pernet, and Amos Storkey.

2010 Harvard Medical School, Cambridge, USA

Visiting Research Fellow

Work at Surgical Planning Laboratory. Collaboration with Dr Alex Golby (Harvard) and Dr Satrajit

Ghosh (MIT).

2008 – 2009 University of Edinburgh, UK

MRes with Distinction in Neuroinformatics

Thesis topic: "Noise Contributions to Functional Diffusion Tensor Imaging", supervisor: Mark Bastin

2004 - 2008 Poznan University of Technology, Poland

BSc in Computer Science

Graduated with grade A (excellent), merit-based scholarship

Grants

- ➤ NIH R24 BIDS-Derivatives: A data standard for derived data and models 2017 (\$955k over 2 years)
- ➤ Laura and John Arnold Foundation Grant to fund Center for Reproducible Neuroscience 2015 (\$3.7 million over 3 years)
- > INCF Special Grant for development of NeuroVault.org, 2014 (20k EUR over 6 months)

Professional Society and Technical Committee Activities

- General Chair of the Open Science Special Interest Group at the Organization for Human Brain Mapping
 2017-2018
- > Programme chair of the 2017 Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging Workshop

Most notable projects

- ➤ **Nipype** a flexible Python framework for building and efficiently running neuroimaging data processing pipelines. A vibrant open source project with >100 contributors. https://github.com/nipy/nipype
- > NeuroVault.org a repository for sharing and analysis of statistical maps of the human brain. Since launch in 2013 amassed 36k brain maps and >300 paper mentions. http://NeuroVault.org
- ➤ Brain Imaging Data Structure a community driven standard for organizing and describing neuroimaging data. Adopted by projects such as OpenfMRI, FCP-INDI, SchizConnect and Developing Human Connectome Project as well as a growing number of labs around the world. http://bids.neuroimaging.io
- ➤ MRIQC and FMRIPREP a pair of apps for quality control and robust preprocessing of neuroimaging data. Downloaded ~20k times. https://github.com/poldracklab/mriqc and https://github.com/poldracklab/mriqc
- > **OpenNeuro.org** a science as a service platform delivering reproducible computationally expensive analysis as an incentive for data sharing. First of its kind. http://openneuro.org

Publications

Statistics:

- ➤ Google Scholar: citation count: 1537, h-index: 22
- > Semantic Scholar: citation count: 3118, citation velocity: 1044

Journal Articles and selected conference papers

Gorgolewski, K. J., Durnez, J., & Poldrack, R. A. (2017). Preprocessed Consortium for Neuropsychiatric Phenomics dataset. F1000Research, 6.

Gorgolewski, K. J., Thomas Nichols, David N Kennedy, Jean-Baptiste Poline, and Russell A Poldrack. 2017. "Promoting Replications through Positive Incentives." Figshare. doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.5278327.v1.

Esteban, O., Birman, D., Schaer, M., Koyejo, O. O., Poldrack, R. A., & Gorgolewski, K. J. (accepted). MRIQC: Predicting Quality in Manual MRI Assessment Protocols Using No-Reference Image Quality Measures. PLoS ONE.

Kiar, G., **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, Kleissas, D., Roncal, W. G., Litt, B., Wandell, B., Poldrack, R. A., et al. (2017). Science In the Cloud (SIC): A use case in MRI Connectomics. GigaScience.

Acikalin, M. Y., **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, & Poldrack, R. A. (2017). A Coordinate-Based Meta-Analysis of Overlaps in Regional Specialization and Functional Connectivity across Subjective Value and Default Mode Networks. Frontiers in neuroscience, 11, 1.

Poldrack, R. A., Congdon, E., Triplett, W., Gorgolewski, K. J., Karlsgodt, K. H., Mumford, J. A., Sabb, F. W., et al. (2016). A phenome-wide examination of neural and cognitive function. Scientific data, 3, 160110.

Poldrack, R. A., Baker, C. I., Durnez, J., Gorgolewski, K. J., Matthews, P. M., Munafò, M. R., Nichols, T. E., et al. (2017). Scanning the horizon: towards transparent and reproducible neuroimaging research. Nature reviews. Neuroscience. Nature Research.

Pernet, C. R., Gorgolewski, K. J., Job, D., Rodriguez, D., Whittle, I., & Wardlaw, J. (2016). A structural and functional magnetic resonance imaging dataset of brain tumour patients. Scientific data, 3, 160003.

Gorgolewski, K. J., Alfaro-Almagro, F., Auer, T., Bellec, P., Capota, M., Mallar Chakravarty, M., Churchill, N. W., et al. (2017). BIDS Apps: Improving ease of use, accessibility and reproducibility of neuroimaging data analysis methods. Plos Computational Biology. [OA]

Gorgolewski, K. J., & Poldrack, R. A. (2016). A Practical Guide for Improving Transparency and Reproducibility in Neuroimaging Research. PLoS biology, 14(7), e1002506. [OA]

- Gorgolewski, K. J., Auer, T., Calhoun, V. D., Craddock, R. C., Das, S., Duff, E. P., Flandin, G., et al. (2016). The brain imaging data structure, a format for organizing and describing outputs of neuroimaging experiments. Scientific data, 3, 160044. [OA]
- Sochat, V. V., Gorgolewski, K. J., Koyejo, O., Durnez, J., & Poldrack, R. A. (2015). Effects of thresholding on correlation-based image similarity metrics. Frontiers in neuroscience, 9. Frontiers. [OA]
- Shine, J. M., Oluwasanmi, K., Bell, P. T., **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, Gilat, M., & Poldrack, R. A. (2015). Estimation of dynamic functional connectivity using Multiplicative Analytical Coupling. NeuroImage.
- Pernet, C. R., McAleer, P., Latinus, M., **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, Charest, I., Bestelmeyer, P. E. G., Watson, R. H., et al. (2015). The human voice areas: Spatial organization and inter-individual variability in temporal and extra-temporal cortices. NeuroImage, 119, 164–174.
- Poldrack, R. A., & Gorgolewski, K. J. (2015). OpenfMRI: Open sharing of task fMRI data. NeuroImage.
- Shine, J. M., Oluwasanmi, K., Bell, P. T., Gorgolewski, K. J., Gilat, M., & Poldrack, R. A. (2015). Estimation of dynamic functional connectivity using Multiplicative Analytical Coupling. NeuroImage.
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Varoquaux, G., Rivera, G., Schwartz, Y., Sochat, V. V., Ghosh, S. S., Maumet, C., et al. (2015). NeuroVault.org: A repository for sharing unthresholded statistical maps, parcellations, and atlases of the human brain. NeuroImage.
- **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, Varoquaux, G., Rivera, G., Schwarz, Y., Ghosh, S. S., Maumet, C., Sochat, V. V., et al. (2015). NeuroVault.org: a web-based repository for collecting and sharing unthresholded statistical maps of the human brain. Frontiers in neuroinformatics, 9. Frontiers. [OA]
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Mendes, N., Wilfling, D., Wladimirow, E., Gauthier, C., Bonnen, T., Ruby, F. J. M., et al. (2015). A high resolution 7-Tesla resting-state fMRI test-retest dataset with cognitive and physiological measures. Scientific Data. [OA]
- Zuo, X-N., Anderson, J., Pierre Bellec, P., Birn, B., Biswal, B., Blautzik, J., Breitner, J., Buckner, R., Calhoun, V., Castellanos, F., Chen, A., Chen, B., Chen, J., Chen, X., Colcombe, S., Courtney, W., Craddock, C., Di Martino, A., Dong, H-M., Fu, X., Gong, Q., Gorgolewski, K. J., et al.. (2014). An Open Science Resource for Establishing Reliability and Reproducibility in Functional Connectomics. Scientific Data. [OA]
- Poldrack, R. A. and Gorgolewski, K. J. (2014) Making big data open: Data sharing in neuroimaging. 17(11), 1510–1517. Nature Neuroscience [OA]*
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Lurie, D., Urchs, S., Kipping, J. A., Craddock, R. C., Milham, M. P., Margulies, D. S., et al. (2014). A correspondence between individual differences in the brain's intrinsic functional architecture and the content and form of self-generated thoughts. PloS one, 9(5), e97176. [OA]
- Schaefer, A., Margulies, D. S., Lohmann, G., **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, Smallwood, J., Kiebel, S. J., & Villringer, A. (2014). Dynamic network participation of functional connectivity hubs assessed by resting-state fMRI. Frontiers in human neuroscience, 8, 195. [OA]
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Storkey, A. J., Bastin, M. E., Whittle, I., & Pernet, C. (2013). Single subject fMRI test-retest reliability metrics and confounding factors. NeuroImage, 69, 231–243. [OA]*
- Baird, B., Smallwood, J., Gorgolewski, K. J., & Margulies, D. S. (2013). Medial and Lateral Networks in Anterior Prefrontal Cortex Support Metacognitive Ability for Memory and Perception. Journal of Neuroscience, 33(42), 16657–16665. [OA]*
- Margulies, D. S., Böttger, J., Watanabe, A., & Gorgolewski, K. J. (2013). Visualizing the human connectome. NeuroImage, 80, 445–461. Elsevier B.V. [OA]*
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Margulies, D. S., & Milham, M. P. (2013). Making Data Sharing Count: A Publication-Based Solution. Frontiers in brain imaging methods, 7. Frontiers in human neuroscience [OA]
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Bazin, P.-L., Engen, H., & Margulies, D. S. (2013). Fifty Shades of Gray, Matter: Using Bayesian priors to improve the power of whole-brain voxel- and connexelwise inferences. Pattern Recognition in NeuroImaging (PRNI), 2013 International Workshop on. [OA]
- Smallwood, J., Gorgolewski, K. J., Golchert, J., Ruby, F. J. M., Engen, H., Baird, B., Vinski, M. T., et al. (2013). The default modes of reading: modulation of posterior cingulate and medial prefrontal cortex connectivity associated with comprehension and task focus while reading. Frontiers in human neuroscience, 7(November), 1–10. [OA]
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Storkey, A., Bastin, M. E., Whittle, I. R., Wardlaw, J. M., & Pernet, C. R. (2013). A test-retest fMRI dataset for motor, language and spatial attention functions. GigaScience, 2(1), 6. [OA]
- Buchanan, C. R., Pernet, C. R., Gorgolewski, K. J., Storkey, A. J., & Bastin, M. E. (2013). Test-retest reliability of structural brain networks from diffusion MRI. NeuroImage. [OA]*
- Poline, J.-B., Breeze, J. L., Ghosh, S., **Gorgolewski, K. J.**, Halchenko, Y. O., Hanke, M., Haselgrove, C., et al. (2012). Data sharing in neuroimaging research. Frontiers in human neuroscience, 6(April), 1–13. [OA]
- Gorgolewski, K. J., Storkey, A. J., Bastin, M. E., & Pernet, C. R. (2012). Adaptive thresholding for reliable topological inference in single subject fMRI analysis. Frontiers in human neuroscience, 6, 1–14. [OA]

Gorgolewski, K. J., Burns, C. D., Madison, C., Clark, D., Halchenko, Y. O., Waskom, M. L., & Ghosh, S. S. (2011). Nipype: A Flexible, Lightweight and Extensible Neuroimaging Data Processing Framework in Python. Frontiers in neuroinformatics, 5(August). [OA]

Awards

- > OHBM Abstract Merit award, 2015
- > OHBM Travel Award, 2013
- ➤ ISMRM Educational Stipend, 2011
- > Edinburgh Neuroscience Neuroresearcher Fund, 2011
- > Neuroinformatics and Computational Neuroscience Doctoral Training Centre Fellowship, 2008-2012

Invited talks

- > Towards open and reproducible neuroscience in the age of big data Imperial College London September 2017
- > OpenNeuro.org: a free online platform for sharing and analysis of neuroimaging data OHBM 2017
- > Towards open and reproducible neuroscience in the age of big data MIT February 2017
- > Towards open and reproducible neuroscience in the age of big data NIH January 2017
- > Brain Imaging Data Structure, June 2016 Organization for Human Brain Mapping 2016
- > Brain Imaging Data Structure and Center for Reproducible Neuroscience. December 2015, Montreal Neurological Institute, Canada
- > Brain Imaging Data Structure. INCF Congress, August 2015, Cairns
- > Data sharing in neuroimaging: incentives, tools, and challenges. February 2015, Albuquerque
- > Some neuroinformatics tools for data sharing and reproducibility. December 2014, Berkeley
- > NeuroVault and the vision for data sharing in neuroimaging. January 2014, London
- > Data processing for MRI resting state. September 2013, York
- > Data processing using Nipype beginners workshop. May 2013, Trento
- > Nipype Connectivity Workshop. September 2012, Magdeburg
- > Using fMRI for presurgical planning: advancements in statistical methods. May 2012 Leipzig
- > Data processing using Nipype. April 2012, Iowa City
- > Data processing using Nipype. April 2012, Munich

Teaching experience

- Sharing data & code for Reproducible NeuroImaging. Birmingham, Oxford, and Glasgow 2017
- > Best practices for reproducible neuroscience. Seattle 2017, NeuroHackWeek
- ➤ Better Science, Los Angeles 2017
- > Docker for scientists. Seattle 2016, NeuroHackWeek
- > How to organize and share data easily and at low cost. Geneva 2016, Organization for Human Brain Mapping Educational Session
- > Brain Data Sharing, Trento June 2016, Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging (PRNI) Tutorial
- > Advanced fMRI Methods, Beijing 5 day hands on course, (2015)
- ➤ Invited Lecturer: Berkeley neuroimaging class (2014)
- ➤ Lecturer: Introduction to Research Computing, 2010-2011
- > Teaching Assistant: Data Mining and Exploration, 2009-2011
- > Tutor: Processing Natural and Formal Languages (2009-2010), Introduction to Applied Machine Learning (2009-2010), Machine Learning and Pattern Recognition (2010-2011)
- > Supervision of numerous interns and masters students.

Other experience

> INCF Data Sharing Task Force

Active member since 2010.

> Neuroimaging Data Processing Workshop, Edinburgh 2010

Organized a two day INCF founded workshop with international speakers for 30 participants.

> IDEA Sequence Development course, Boston 2010

Five day long Siemens MRI sequence programming course.

> Leading developer of Nipype data processing software

Actively involved in development and user support since 2009.

> Software Developer Engineer at Microsoft

Summer 2008 internship with Content Access Protection team - Redmond, WA, USA.

Skills

- > Neuroimaging: paradigm design (Presentation and OpenSesame) and analysis of fMRI, DTI, T1, T2 data using SPM, FSL, Freesurfer, Diffusion Toolkit, MRTrix, and Nipy
- > Software development: C, C++, C#, Java, Python, Django, MATLAB, Git, and SVN

- ➤ System administration: Linux
 ➤ Statistics and machine learning: R, SPSS, sklearn
 ➤ https://github.com/chrisfilo